in this video i'm going to show you
everything you need to know to use
sketchup to create stuff like this
this or this using sketchup free right
in your browser all within the next 10
minutes and you don't need to know
anything about 3d modeling or sketchup
this tutorial is for complete beginners
so go to app.sketchup.com
create a free account click create new
and let's build this table together
so click on the rectangle tool click
once to pin the first corner and then
move your mouse out to expand the
rectangle now the bottom right hand
corner of your window will show you the
current measurement information you're
working with and you can actually just
start typing in measurements and press
enter in order to model precisely so
let's make this rectangle 18 inches by
18 inches so the first important rule to
remember is all drawing and modification
tools will accept dimensional input from
you just start typing in dimensions and
press enter now if you screw up just
press ctrl z to undo or you can actually
correct dimensions by providing new ones
as many times as you'd like as long as
you don't start a new action or activate
a new tool now if you do that you'll
just have to use one of the modification
tools to resize the entities directly
but we're going to review those later on
for now let's add some thickness to this
table top by using the push pull tool
here so click once pull up
type three quarter inch enter
now you can use decimals fractions feet
inches millimeters centimeters whatever
you want sketchup really doesn't care it
all just works so congratulations you
now have your very first 3d object now
before you do anything else
you need to protect these entities by
wrapping them in a group or component
and you do that by triple clicking the
entities with the select tool right
click make group now all of these
entities are wrapped inside of a
protective container so they won't stick
to other entities and it'll allow you to
move all of them as one assembly now you
should be using groups and components
all the time as soon as you have a basic
shape turn it into a group or component
now when you have multiple groups and
components turn those into logical
assemblies as well and you can nest
groups and components as much as you'd
like all right so how do you navigate
use a three button mouse
scroll to zoom now it's going to zoom
from the mouse cursor position and then
to orbit the camera click the middle
mouse button which is typically the
scroll wheel so hold the middle mouse
button move the mouse then release and
then repeat as necessary
bonus tip hold down shift while orbiting
to pan alright so let's move the table
top up into position select the table
top group with the select tool activate
the move tool and since we know the
distance and direction we want to move
and the table is pre-selected we can
actually just click anywhere to start
the move tap the up arrow to lock the
blue axis
and type in 26 and three quarters of an
inch enter let's add a bevel orbit the
camera so you can see the bottom of the
table top and in order to edit the
entities inside of any group or
component you just need to open it first
by double clicking on it with the select
tool now you can edit the individual
faces and edges so everything in
sketchup is made up of edges and faces
they are the most
fundamental entity type of all geometry
and once you understand that you realize
that every single drawing tool in
sketchup simply provides a way to create
edges and faces and all the modification
tools simply change the size position or
orientation of edges and faces now the
rectangle tool automates the process of
creating four edges in one face but you
could actually create the exact same
thing using the line tool there's
literally no difference between these
two rectangles they're just four edges
in one face now the arc tools circle
tool polygon tools follow the same
principle but they do employ
an additional special entity wrapper to
make it easier to control curves which
are technically just series of segmented
edges to add the bevel on the table grab
the offset tool here click on the face
move the mouse inward click again and
type 2 inch enter next select each of
the perimeter edges by holding the ctrl
key with the select tool then grab the
move tool click once tap the up arrow
then type in
quarter inch enter and you can see we
now have this little bevel here and now
that we're done with the table top we
can close the group by clicking
somewhere outside of the bounding box
with the select tool and now we can
start modeling the table legs create a
square at this corner at 1 1 8 by 1 in 1
8 next grab the push-pull tool and
extrude this down to the ground so you
can snap to the origin so you don't have
to type in a distance next we need to
turn this into a component components
let you have identical copies where you
can edit one and have all the other
copies update too so triple click right
click make component give it a name and
click ok let's add the taper to the leg
so double click the component to open it
for editing and notice how the tabletop
becomes grayed out you can use hide rest
of model to hide everything outside of
the current context let's use the tape
measure tool to create a guide where we
want the taper to start grab the tape
measure tool click on the top edge here
to create a guide parallel from it move
the mouse downward along the blue axis
and type in 6 inch enter
now we can reference the guides using
the line tool to subdivide the faces
where we want the taper so remember to
use the arrow keys to lock axes it's
just a good habit to get into so you
know you're drawing a long axis once the
lines are drawn we can go down to the
bottom here and use the scale tool to
scale the bottom of the leg inward by a
factor of 0.5 and you can use the scale
tool on any selection and you can
provide it either a scale factor or an
absolute dimension
okay so now let's exit the component and
copy some legs to each corner of the
table we can actually create copies
using the move tool so select the leg
grab the move tool and click on this
specific point right here
tap control to activate copy mode and
move it to this specific point on the
tabletop now since we're using the
inference system for this move we don't
need to type in a dimension now you'll
notice that the taper is facing the
wrong way so we need to rotate this copy
90 degrees and an easy way to do that is
to use the built-in rotation grips that
appear on selected groups and components
when you have the move tool active and
so you can repeat this for the other two
legs but if you're feeling up for it i
want to show you an advanced way to do
this using the rotate tool so i can show
you some advanced infant system tricks
while we're at it so select the leg grab
the rotate tool and the rotate tool will
orient according to which face you're
hovering over but like most tools in
sketchup wink wink
you can lock the orientation using the
up left right or down arrow key now i
haven't told you about the down arrow
key yet but it's an inference lock that
lets you inference edges and faces in
your model that aren't aligned to one of
the three axes so let's go ahead and
lock the blue axis with the up arrow key
and just like the move tool you can use
the rotate tool to make copies too so
let's rotate three copies around the
center of the table but how do you
actually find the center point well if
you hover over an inference point for
about a second or two sketchup will
temporarily track from that point and
the cool thing is you can do this with
two inference points which will then
allow you to find their intersection and
from there we just click to place the
rotation point tap control to switch to
copy mode click again to establish the
reference line then move the mouse until
you snap to 90 degrees and click to
place the first copy next type in 3x
enter and that will place three copies
in total now you can create areas like
this with the move tool too by using
either a multiplication sign or division
sign depending on where you want the
copies to be arrayed then just use
everything you've learned so far to add
the aprons rails and drawer remember to
use groups and components for everything
now if you find the table top getting in
your way as you model you can click on
tags add a new tag then with the tag
selected you can click on the table top
to apply it to the group and now you can
control the visibility of the top by
toggling this icon right here you can
find materials to apply to your model
right here just click on a swatch to
activate the paint bucket tool and apply
the material to the model you can also
change the look of your model using
styles here so styles control a variety
of different visual properties to
dramatically change the look of your
model
now there are a ton of additional
features tips and workflows that i
haven't covered
in this video so if this is your first
time on my channel my name is matt
donnelly and i'm a sketchup teacher and
author you can find my books in the
links below and make sure you subscribe
to my channel to get more sketchup
tutorials just like this now leave a
comment below if there's any part of the
video you got stuck on or if you'd like
me to make a video on a specific
sketchup topic alright that's it for
this video thanks for watching and i'll
see you in the next video